A Guide to the W.E. Long & Sons General Store Collection, 1865-1971
Special Collections, Carrier Library, James Madison University
Special Collections, James Madison University
W.E. Long & Sons General Store Collection, 1865-1971
Special Collections, James Madison University
SC 5044
7 boxes (3.25 linear feet)
The W.E. Long & Sons General Store Collection, 1865-1971, consists of seven boxes containing 1014 items pertaining to the business transacted at W. E. Long & Sons General Store. The collection is arranged into six series: 1.) Invoices, Advertisements, and Correspondence. 2.) Purchases and Orders. 3.) Bank Ledgers, Expenses, and Sales. 4.) Long's Stores Account Books. 5.) Long's Store Records. 6.) Mt. Clinton Post Office Records.
William E. Long
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
None
Acquisition Information
Collection was purchased from Ronald L. Fulk care of Dusty’s Antique Market in Mount Sidney, VA on December 15, 2008. Another part of the collection was purchased from Rocky’s Gold and Silver on July 26, 2009 and merged with the former.
Provenance
The records were collected during the operation of W. E. Long & Sons General Store by its various owners, including Samuel Long, William E. Long, and S. Claude Long, in order to record transactions, expenses, and profit for the store.
Biographical Information
Samuel Long was the original owner of the Long Store. He worked primarily as a farmer and dry goods merchant, running numerous stores before moving from Shenandoah County to Rockingham County in 1868. In 1880, he bought the Hopkins Upper Mill on Muddy Creek and established the Chrisman general store and post office. His son, William E. Long, was named postmaster of the Chrisman post office in 1881. Samuel Long had also established another store around 1869 in Green Mount, Virginia. William E. Long was named postmaster of the Green Mount branch in 1889, and took over operations from J.W. Mauck. In 1892, Samuel Long bought A.B. Driver and Company in Mt. Clinton, Virginia, and changed the name to S. Long & Sons. At this time, William Long was also appointed postmaster of the Mount Clinton post office. William E. Long and his brother-in-law, John B. Bowman ran the Mount Clinton branch of the store under the name Long and Bowman, until the death of Bowman in 1893. Upon the death of Samuel Long in 1897, William’s sister sold her husband’s half of the Mount Clinton store to William for $2,500. The name of the store was changed to W.E. Long and Sons once William Long’s children reached maturity. The store kept this name until it was turned over by William Long’s sons to a nephew, S. Claude Long, who renamed the store S.C. Long & Sons in 1959. It remained under his name until his retirement in 1988 when it left the family’s possession. A quick succession of owners succeeded S. Claude Long until the store was finally torn down in 1995. The Long family owned and operated the Long family store for roughly 95 years, managing to sustain a business through WWI, the Great Depression, and WWII.
Scope and Content
The collection, roughly 3.25 linear feet, consists of receipts, invoices, account books, banks ledgers, postcards, and letters relating to the Long’s Store in Mount Clinton, VA from 1865 to 1971. Also included are advertisements from various companies to the owners of the Long Store. This collection consists of six series: Invoices, Advertisements, and Correspondence, 1865-1955, Purchases and Orders, 1893-1924, and Bank Ledgers, Expenses, and Sales, 1866-1971, Long's Store Account Books, 1869-1921, Long's Records, 1877-1929, Mt. Clinton Post Office Records, 1879-1893
Arrangement
The collection is arranged in 6 series:
I: Invoices, Advertisements, and Correspondence, 1865-1955
II: Purchases and Orders, 1893-1924
III: Bank Ledgers, Expenses, and Sales, 1866-1971
IV: Long's Store Account Books, 1869-1921
V: Long's Store Records, 1877-1929
VI: Mt. Clinton Post Office Records, 1879-1893
Series 1: Invoices, Advertisements and Correspondence, 1865-1955. This series contains invoices to the Long Store from other companies, showing that orders were paid for in full. Specific company invoices include: Harrisonburg Grocery Co. Inc. Exclusively Wholesale, Merchants Grocery and Hardware Co. (Successors of Snell Grocery and Hardware Co.), Sears, Roebuck and Co., Coca-Cola Co., National Biscuit Co. (Nabisco), and the Standard Oil Co. Companies also sent advertisements to the Long Store in order to try to persuade the store to buy their products. Specific company and agency advertisements include advertisements from the US Food Administration, Mishawaka Rubber and Woolen Mfg. Co., Sears, Roebuck and Co., and the Merchants Grocery and Hardware Co. Correspondence includes letters and envelopes addressed to the Long Store from a variety of companies. Most of the correspondence thanks the Long Store for their business, provides information about backordered items, and includes contract letters, and personal correspondence. Companies that sent correspondence letters include; Miller and Yager General Commission Merchants, Superior Dairy Goods Moseley and Stoddard MFG Co., Darby Manufacturing Co., and R. P. Bayley and Co Importers of China and Glass. All of these papers provide insight as to whom the Long Store was conducting business, and their relationships with said businesses. The papers also show the types of products that the people of Mount Clinton, VA were buying not only in everyday life, but also during the war years. The papers are organized chronologically, and they are listed below with the companies in alphabetical order, as well as the number of documents associated with each company. There was a group of advertisements and letters found in Box 3, which contained several letters, which had been left in their original envelopes. The letters were taken out of the envelopes and placed in a folder for preservation. The letters were moved to Series I for convenience sake, and are all contained together in Folder 9, so they do not follow the chronological scheme of the other folders. There is also one postcard from the State Normal School of Harrisonburg, VA, which seemingly has no connection to the Long family, but was found in with the ledgers.
Series 2: Purchases and Orders, 1893-1924. This series contains purchases and orders in ledgers compiled during the lifetime of the Long Store. The series contains 23 ledgers in total. Some ledgers show what the people ordered from the store and others show what the Long Store purchased from other companies in order to fulfill the needs of their customers. The order ledgers show what the people wanted to buy as well as who the regular customers were. They show the relationship that the Long Store had with its customers. Once the orders were delivered and were paid for, the order was crossed out with a red “X,” indicating that the transaction was complete. The purchase ledgers show what the owners of the Long Store purchased in order to meet the demand of their customers. Most of these ledgers are labeled with a date, what was bought on that date, and how much the order cost. Most ledgers were not specific with what goods were bought, but were specific with the pricing. Purchases were mostly labeled as “Goods,” or “Tobacco,” showing the importance of tobacco in that it was given its own category. Other ledgers simply state the name of the company being ordered from, rather than listing all the specific goods themselves.
Series 3: Bank Ledgers, Expenses, and Sales, 1866-1971. This series contains records of the expenses and sales of the Long family store, as well as ten bank ledgers. The majority are specific to the First National Bank of Harrisonburg, VA. These indicate expenses and sales of the store, including specific company or personal names to whom the store is paying off bills or from whom it is receiving payment. There are also three ledgers that indicate expenses of the store. The first ledger appears to be expenses organized by specific person or business. The latter two are organized by type of good, including groceries, tobacco, dry goods, drugs, etc. The orders appear to be crossed out once they were acquired. There are two other larger ledgers in the series. The smaller of the two appears to document the weekly sales of the store. There are several other receipts and calculations relating to the profit of the store stuck in the pages of the ledger. These loose papers were left there in order to preserve original order and context.. The larger of the two ledgers seems to be a system of credit from a store in Johnsonville prior to the existence of Long Family Store in Mt. Clinton, VA. Samuel Long was known to have stores in many locations, so it seems prudent to assume it was one of his stores before Mt. Clinton. As with the previous ledger, there are calculations and a few documents of correspondence stuck in between the pages. They were likewise kept within to preserve original order.
Series 4: Long's Store Account Books, 1869-1921 This series consists of nine books: one "road book" ostensibly from Long's Store in Green Mount, Va. (Rockingham Country); three account books and five daybooks from Long's Store in Mt. Clinton, Va. Daybooks record purchases of general household goods and merchandise, such as eggs, butter, pens, pencils, shoes, yarn, chickens, roosters, sugar, dye, matches, hats, and shovels. Account books typically record customer accounts, transactions and balances over time and do not record itemized purchases.
Series 5: Long's Store Records, 1877-1929 This series is a collection of receipts that document the business between small town merchant W. E. Long and commission merchants such as Miller and Roller, Washington, D.C.; Acker and Long Produce, Philadelphia; Standard Oil Company; Brand Shoe Co., Roanoke; and J. J. Underhill Fruit and Vegetables, Baltimore which he supplied with butter, chicken, and eggs. Among the local merchants are; Snell Grocery, Harrisonburg; Hoge and Hutchinson, Staunton; Merchants Grocery and Hardware, Harrisonburg; L. W. Gaines, Inc., Harrisonburg; Worthington Hardware, Staunton; and National Biscuit Company, Staunton. Bills document the variety of merchandise including shoes, fabric, sugar, and coffee that Long purchased to supply his own customers. 15 Cancelled checks from the First National Bank Harrisonburg date to 1920.
Series 6: Mt. Clinton Post Office Records, 1879-1893 The collection consists of three record books from Mt. Clinton Post Office from 1879 through 1893. All three books are roughly the same size. However, Book One was received missing most of the front and back covers. Book Three was disassembled and boards discarded due to insect damage. William E. long was a postmaster at Chrisman, Va. (1881-1887), Green Mount, Va. (1889-1893), and Mt. Clinton ,Va. (1893-1897). William's father, Samuel, established and operated general stores and post office in all three locations. Why The Mt. Clinton post Office records prior to William's tenure remained in his possession is unclear, as the items in the collection lists his predecessors as Henry Parker and James W. Rhodes.
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Bibliography
MacAllister, Dale. “The William E. Long Family and Long’s Store.”
Contents List
- Invoices, Advertisements, and Correspondence, 1865 - 1955
  - April 1, 1865 - March 31, 1899 (Box-folder 1:1)
    - C.L. Moor
    - Common Wealth of Virginia
    - David Taylor and Co.
    - Hellen Jatzeustler
    - Heller Brothers and Co.
    - Jacob and Viert
    - Joseph Raish and Loans
    - Long Store Ledger Page
    - Rockingham Register
    - R.P. Bayley and Co.
    - Smith, Ellet, and Co.
    - Stoneburner and Richards
    - Treasury of Rockingham County
    - Tucker and Co.
    - Wm. Devries and Co.
    - Young, Kimmell, and Diggs
  - December 3, 1900 - November 6, 1917 (Box-folder 1:2)
    - Baker and Shoe Co.
    - Baltimore Bargain House
    - Baltimore Oil
    - Brand Shoe Co.
    - Byers-Beery Grocery Co.
    - Chesapeake and Ohio RR
    - C.J. Rice
    - Daniel Miller Co. Dry Goods
    - Edelen Bros. Commission
    - First National Bank
    - Harrisonburg Evaporating Co.
    - Harrisonburg Grocery Co.
    - Herb Medicine Co.
    - J.G. Haldeman and Bros.
    - Lynchburg Shoe Co.
    - Miscellaneous
    - Mishawaka Woolen Manufacturing Co.
    - N.K. Fairbank
    - Norfolk Western RR
    - Red C. Oil
    - R.M. Sutton Co.
    - Snell Grocery and Hardware
    - Standard Oil
    - W. A. W. Davis Corporation
  - February 15, 1818 - September 17, 1818 (Box-folder 1:3)
    - American Snuff Co.
    - Baltimore Bargain House
    - Baltimore and Ohio Railroad
    - Crystal Lamps Asst.
    - Daniel Miller Co. Dry Goods
    - Harrisonburg Grocery Co.
    - J. Frank Darling Co. Inc
    - J.W. Ould Company Inc
    - Merchants Grocery and Hardware Co.
    - Red "C" Oul Manufacturing Co.
    - Snell Grocery
    - Southern Railroad Co.
    - US Food Administration
  - December 19, 1921 - December 23, 1924 (Box-folder 1:4)
    - American Wholesale Corporation
    - B.F. Goodrich Rubber
    - Chattanooga Knitting Mills
    - City Produce Exchange
    - Daniel Miller C. Dry Goods
    - Friedman-Shelby International Shoe
    - G.K. Amdrews and Co.
    - Harrisonburg Grocery Co.
    - Imperial Ice Cream Co.
    - J.M. Snell and Co.
    - Merchants Grocery and Hardware Co.
    - National Buscuit Company
    - Sternick and Bittman Butter and Eggs
    - Wetsel Seed Co.
    - W.F. Berry and Son
  - January 5, 1925 - November 1927 (Box-folder 1:5)
    - American Wholesale Corporation
    - Arbuckle Brothers
    - Branhart Overall Company
    - B.F. Goodrich Rubber Company
    - Chas. King. and Son Co, Inc.
    - Daniel Miller Company
    - Edelen Brothers General Commission Merchants
    - Ehrmann Manufacturing Co.
    - First National Bank
    - G.K. Andrews and Co.
    - Harrisonburg Candy and Fruit Company
    - Harrisonburg Grocery Co.
    - International Shoe Company
    - J.M. Strickler
    - John W. Eshelman and Sons
    - J.W. Ould Company
    - L.W. Gaines and Company
    - Merchants Grocery and Hardwarre Co.
    - Mishawaka Rubber and Woolen Mfg. Co.
    - National Biscuit Company
    - Proctor and Gamble Distributing Co.
    - Richmond Hosier Mills
    - Southern Railway Company
    - Valley Supply Company
    - Virginia Cigar Company
    - Wetsel Seed Company
  - February 18, 1928 - December 12, 1928 (Box-folder 1:6)
    - American Wholesale Corporation
    - Barnhart Overall Co.
    - Burke and Prince Insurance
    - Daniel Miller Co. Dry Goods
    - D.D. Ferry and Co. Seedsmen
    - E.W. Ross Ensilage Cutter and Silo. Co.
    - Friedman-Shelby International Shoe
    - Harrisonburg Candy and Fruit Co, Inc.
    - Harrisonburg Grocery Co.
    - Hawkins Hardware Co.
    - H.M. Baucon and Sons
    - J.M. Strickler
    - John. F. Birkmeyer and Sons
    - Merchants Grocery and Hardware Co.
    - Nishawaka Rubber and Woolen Manufacturing Co.
    - National Biscuit Co.
    - R.A. Brice and Son
    - R.G. Dun and Co.
  - January 5, 1929 - November 16, 1929 (Box-folder 1:7)
    - C.D. Kenny Co.
    - Daniel Miller Company
    - Harlin Bro and Co.
    - Harrisonburg Candy and Fruit Company, Inc.
    - Harrisonburg Grocery Co.
    - Hawkins Hardware Co.
    - International Shoe Company
    - Merchants Grocery and Hardware Co.
    - Miscellaneous
    - Mishawaka Rubber and Woolen Mfg. Co.
    - R.A. Brice and Son
    - Sears, Roebuck Company
    - Southern Railway Company
    - Wm. Schlunderburg-T.J. Kurdle Co.
  - March 4, 1930 - September 10, 1955 (Box-folder 1:8)
    - American Wholesale Co.
    - Bentley, Shriver and Co.
    - Bob's Food Products Co., Inc.
    - Butler Brothers
    - Daniel Miller Co. Dry Goods
    - Dixie Distributing Co.
    - E.J. Branch and Sons
    - Elkton Lithia Bottling Co.
    - First National Bank
    - Friedman-Shelby International Shoe
    - Goodyear Tire and Rubber Co., Inc.
    - Harrisonburg Candy and Fruit Company, Inc.
    - Harrisonburg Grocery Company
    - Harrisonburg Livestock Market Inc.
    - Hartford Fire Insurance Co.
    - Henry S. King and Sons
    - J.F. Burkholder's Speech on World Peace
    - J.S. Denton and Sons, Inc.
    - Manbeck Bread Co.
    - Merchants Grocery and Hardware Co.
    - Miscellaneous Accounting
    - M.O. Showalter and Son
    - National Biscuit Co.
    - Ort Brothers Bakery, Inc.
    - Proctor and Gamble Distributing Co.
    - Rockingham Cooperative Farm Bureau, Inc.
    - Rockingham Tractor and Equipment Co.
    - Snow King Baking Powder Co.
    - Strietman Biscuit Co.
    - Virginia Pepsi-Cola Bottling Co.
    - Wm. Schluderberg- T.J. Kurdle Co.
  - February 1, 1882 - June 24, 1911 (Box:folder 1:9)
    - R.P. Bayley and Co Importers of China and Glass
    - Miller and Yager General Commission Merchants: invoice/envelope, 1882 February 2
    - Miller and yager General Commission Merchants: invoice/envelope, 1882 November 10
    - Superior Dairy Goods Moseley and Stoddard MFG Co.: 4 ads/envelope, c. 1887
    - George G. McClintock Commission merchants: receipt.envelope, 1892 August 2
    - Darby Manufacturing Co.: envelope, 1892 August 25
    - Edelen Bros Commission Merchants: Invoice/Envelope 3:30/1901
    - State Normal School Postcard, 1911 June 25
- Purchases and Orders, 1893 - 1924
  - Customer Order Ledger 1:, November, 1899 - December, 1899 (Box 2)
  - Customer Order Ledger 2:, April, 1900 - October, 1900
  - Customer Order Ledger 3:, October, 1900 - August, 1901
  - Customer Order Ledger 4
  - Customer Order Ledger 5:, September, 1902 - April, 1903
  - Customer Order Ledger 6:, April, 1903 - August, 1903
  - Customer Order Ledger 7:, June, 1904 - August, 1904
  - Customer Order Ledger 8:, April, 1907 - May, 1907
  - Customer Order Ledger 9:, April, 1909 - June, 1909
  - Purchase Ledger Marker "To Goods" 1:, April, 1893 - March, 1904
  - Purchase Ledger Marker "To Goods" 2:, January, 1907 - January, 1908
  - Purchase Ledger with Specific Goods Listed 1:, January, 1906 - January, 1907
  - Purchase Ledger with Specific Goods Listed 2:, January, 1907 - January, 1908
  - Purchase Ledger with Specific Goods Listed 3:, January, 1910 - 1911
  - Purchase Ledger with Specific Goods Listed 4:, 1911 - 1913
  - Purchase Ledger with Specific Goods Listed 5:, 1913 - 1915
  - Purchase Ledger with Specific Goods Listed 6
  - Purchase Ledger with Specific Goods Listed 7:, 1914
  - Purchase Ledger with Company Names Listed 1:, April, 1917 - December, 1919
  - Purchase Ledger with Company Names Listed 2:, July, 1921 - June, 1922
  - Purchase Ledger with Company Names Listed 3:, August, 1922 - July, 1923
  - Purchase Ledger with Company Names Listed 4:, August, 1923 - March, 1924
- Banke Ledgers, Expenses and Sales, 1866 - 1971
  - Bank Ledger 1:, April, 1903 - August, 1905 (Box 3)
  - Bank Ledger 2:, September, 1905 - January, 1908
  - Bank Ledger 3:, January, 1908 - March, 1910
  - Bank Ledger 4:, June, 1912 - August, 1914
  - Bank Ledger 5:, August, 1913 - Augsust, 1914
  - Bank Ledger 6:, August, 1914 - February, 1915
  - Bank Ledger 7:, February, 1915 - December, 1915
  - Bank Ledger 8:, February, 1918 - June, 1921
  - Bank Ledger 9:, July, 1926 - June, 1927
  - Bank Ledger 10:, July, 1932 - March, 1935
  - Expense Ledger 1:, April, 1893 - October, 1900
  - Expense Ledger (Organized by Type of Good) 2
  - Expense Ledger (Organized by Type of Good) 3:, 1901
  - Weekley Sales (Large Ledger), January, 1919 - December, 1971
  - Johnsonville Ledger, October, 1866 - March, 1868
- Long's Stores Account Books, 1869 - 1921
  - Book One: Daybook, December, 1869 - January, 1871 (Box-folder 4:4)
  - Book Four: Daybook, November, 1902 - September, 1903 (Box:folder 4:5)
  - Book Five: Daybook, November, 1905 - May, 1906 (Box:folder 5:1)
  - Book Six: Daybook, June - December, 1917 (Box:folder 5:2)
  - Book Eight: Daybook, May - November, 1921 (Box:folder 5:3)
  - Book Nine: Account Book (Undated) (Box:folder 5:4)
  - Book Seven: Accountbook, August 1918 - September, 1921 (Box:folder 6:1)
  - Book Three: Daybook, January - August, 1901 (Box:folder 6:2)
  - Book Two: Accountbook, August, 1900 - July, 1903 (Box:folder 6:3)
- Long's Store Records, 1877 - 1929
  - Bills and Receipts, 1877-1894 (Box-folder 7:1)
  - Bills and Receipts, 1895 (Box-folder 7:2)
  - Bills and Receipts, 1896 - 1899 (Box-folder 7:3)
  - Bills and Receipts, 1900 - 1922 (Box-folder 7:4)
  - Bills and Receipts, 1923 (Box-folder 7:5)
  - Bills and Receipts, 1924 - 1929 (Box-folder 7:6)
  - Price Lists, 1880 - 1924 (Box-folder 7:7)
- Mt. Clinton Post Office Records, 1879 - 1893
  - Book One, September, 1879 - March, 1883 (Box-folder 4:1)
  - Book Two, April, 1883 - March, 1888 (Box-folder 4:2)
  - Book 3, October 1884 - December 1893 (Box-folder 4:3)